A Guide to the Mason Family Papers, 1756-1891
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Mason Family Papers, 1756-1891
Library of Virginia
23684
0.9 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Mason family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Board of Regents of Gunston Hall, Mason Neck, Virginia, 14 May 1951
Family History
The Mason family were residents of Sussex County, Virginia. John Mason, Jr. (1741-1802) was the son of Major John Mason (ca. 1716-1785) and Elizabeth Chappell (1723-1799). He was a member of the Committee of Safety for Sussex County, and a captain in the county militia. He married (1) Elizabeth Gee around 1760, and (2) Jane Parham in September 1764. Their son John Raines Mason was born on 24 April 1770. He was a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, justice of the peace, and sherriff of Sussex County. He married (1) Lucy Massenburg around 1790, and (2) Sarah Harrison Cargill. He died in December 1826.
Scope and Contents
Papers, 1765-1891, of the Mason family of Sussex County, Virginia, most notably John Mason, Jr. (1741-1802) and his son John Raines Mason (1770-1826). The bulk of the collection covers the years 1780 to 1820. Includes accounts, agreements, bonds, correspondence, estate papers, promissory notes, receipts, suit papers, and other items.
The estate papers concern the estates of Nathaniel Duncan, William Harrison, Jr., Dr. Robert Irwin, Daniel Ivey, Thomas Johnson, James Mason, John Mason, William Mason, Henry Parsons, Launcelot Stone, and William Underhill. Also included are copies of the will and inventory of Thomas Epes of Prince George County, and an opinion on the settlement of his estate by Edmund Randolph, as well as a portion of the will of John Thweatt, also of Prince George County.
Contents List
- Accounts, 1762-1779 (Box 1:1)
- Accounts, 1780-1789 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Accounts, 1790-1799 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Accounts, 1800-1809 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Accounts, 1813-1836 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Agreements, 1797-1799 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Bill of Sale for Land, 1813 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Bonds, 1770-1802 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Bonds - Fragments (Box-folder 1:10)
- Commissions to Examine Witnesses, 1786, 1788 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Correspondence, 1771, 1777-1779 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Correspondence, 1780-1789 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Correspondence, 1790-1799 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Correspondence, 1800-1804 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Correspondence, 1805-1809 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Correspondence, 1810-1819 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Correspondence, 1820-1823 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Correspondence, 1877, 1890-1891 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Correspondence, n.d. (Box-folder 1:20)
- Correspondence - Fragments (Box-folder 1:21)
- Deed - Fragment (Box-folder 1:22)
- Deed of Emancipation, 1795 (Box-folder 1:23)
- Deeds, 1763, 1777, 1783 (Box-folder 1:24)
- Estate Papers - Duncan, Nathaniel (Box-folder 2:1)
- Estate Papers - Harrison, William, Jr. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Estate Papers - Irwin, Robert, Dr. (Box-folder 2:3)
- Estate Papers - Ivey, Daniel (Box-folder 2:4)
- Estate Papers - Johnson, Thomas (Box-folder 2:5)
- Estate Papers - Mason, James (Box-folder 2:6)
- Estate Papers - Mason, John (Box-folder 2:7)
- Estate Papers - Mason, William (Box-folder 2:8)
- Estate Papers - Parsons, Henry (Box-folder 2:9)
- Estate Papers - Stone, Launcelot (Box-folder 2:10)
- Estate Papers - Underhill, William (Box-folder 2:11)
- Guardian's Accounts, 1783-1784 (Box-folder 2:12)
- List of Negroes of John Mason, n.d. (Box-folder 2:13)
- Marriage License, Joseph Drury and Emma Simmons, Southampton County, 1821 (Box-folder 2:14)
- Memorandum of Expenses in the West Indies, 1788 (Box-folder 2:15)
- Militia Fines, 1802 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 2:17)
- Miscellaneous Fragments (Box-folder 2:18)
- Oath, 1776 (Box-folder 2:19)
- Plats and Surveys (Box-folder 2:20)
- Power to Sell Negroes of Willie Jones and Walter Jones, 1802 (Box-folder 2:21)
- Promissory Notes, 1773-1813 (Box-folder 2:22)
- Receipts, 1756 (Box-folder 2:23)
- Receipts, 1761, 1763, 1769 (Box-folder 2:24)
- Receipts, 1770-1779 (Box-folder 2:25)
- Receipts, 1780-1789 (Box-folder 2:26)
- Receipts, 1790-1792 (Box-folder 2:27)
- Receipts, 1793-1795 (Box-folder 2:28)
- Receipts, 1796-1799 (Box-folder 2:29)
- Receipts, 1800-1801 (Box-folder 2:30)
- Receipts, 1802-1804 (Box-folder 2:31)
- Receipts, 1805-1809 (Box-folder 2:32)
- Receipts, 1810-1819 (Box-folder 2:33)
- Receipts, 1820-1838 (Box-folder 2:34)
- Receipts, n.d. (Box-folder 2:35)
- Receipts - Court Fees, 1769-1825 (Box-folder 2:36)
- Receipts - Fragments (Box-folder 2:37)
- Road Papers, 1794 (Box-folder 2:38)
- Slave Bills of Sale, 1769, 1778 (Box-folder 2:39)
- Suit Papers, 1768, 1772, 1795-1813 (Box-folder 2:40)
- Tax Receipts, 1782-1837 (Box-folder 2:41)
- Unidentified Estate Inventory (Box-folder 2:42)
- Will and Estate Inventory of Thomas Epes (copies), 1779-1780 (Box-folder 2:43)
- Will (portion) of John Thweatt, 1758 (Box-folder 2:44)